Moving on to valvular disorders,
let's remind ourselves of some basic anatomy.
Of course, the heart has four valves.
Here's the right atrium, right ventricle,
left atrium, and left ventricle.
There is a tricuspid valve here.
There is a pulmonary valve here,
a mitral valve here,
and then an aortic valve here.
Now, of course, the idea is that the valves
help to prevent backflow
as blood is being pushed forward through the system,
and the disorders of the valves are basically two.
One is when you get stenosis,
and so, for example, you can get stenosis of the aortic valve.
When you get stenosis, that tightens the orifice of the valve,
it narrows the orifice of the valve,
which then makes it harder to push blood through.
The other possibility would be
that you can get regurg of the valve.
For example, if you had mitral valve regurg,
that would allow backflow across the valve,
and so these are the two types of pathologies
that are going to arise
as we move forward in our discussion.
The very first topic that we want to cover
is acute rheumatic fever.
Now, this is a systemic complication
of a group A beta hemolytic strep infection of the throat,
usually seen in children two to three weeks
after the strep throat,
and what happens is you generate an immune response
against the bacteria,
and the bacteria has M proteins,
and these M proteins are antigens
that resemble antigens in human tissues,
and so, therefore, as you're generating a response
against the M proteins,
you begin to generate a response against human tissues,
and that results in damage to tissues,
and then, of course, acute rheumatic fever.
Now, it's important to note,
in very high yield for exams,
that this notion of the bacterial M protein
resembling human tissues is called molecular mimicry,
and the board examiners like you to know that term,
molecular mimicry.
When you'd like to make a diagnosis of acute rheumatic fever,
you do so using the Jones criteria.
Now, the first thing that you need is evidence
of a prior group A beta hemolytic strep infection.
For example, anti-streptolysin O titers,
or anti-DNA speed titers.
These are both markers of a prior group A
beta hemolytic strep infection.
In addition, you could identify minor criteria,
such as fever and elevated ESR,
and then there's a series of major criteria,
and it's important to know each of them.
Now, I use the first letters of the word Jones
in order to remind me of the criteria.
Of course, these are called the Jones criteria.
So the J reminds me that you're gonna get joint problems,
and the key problem here would be a migratory polyarthritis,
where you get arthritis of a large joint,
such as the wrist, knees, or ankles,
and then it resolves and moves to another large joint.
The O sort of reminds us that there's going to be
heart problems, and the heart problems are pancarditis,
where you get inflammation of each of the layers of the heart.
And so you get a endocarditis, a myocarditis,
and a pericarditis.
And we'll talk about the inflammation of the heart
in a little more detail in a moment.
The N reminds us of the fact that we're going to have
nodules in the skin, so you get subcutaneous nodules.
The E stands for erythema marginatum.
Erythema marginatum is a rash that appears more red
at the margins of the rash.
It's an annular rash that has erythematous borders,
so hence the term marginatum,
because it's more red at the margins.
And finally, the S reminds us of syndenhems chorea.
So recall that these patients can have rapid involuntary movements
of their muscle, which, of course, is called chorea.
And so these are the five major criteria of acute rheumatic fever.
Now, of these five, the joint problems, the nodules, the erythema,
and the syndenhems chorea will all resolve with time,
and there are no long-term sequelae.
But the key problem is going to be the heart problem,
and so we want to focus on that a little bit.
So let me just remind you that the heart problems are going to be a pancarditis.
And by pancarditis, we mean that each of the layers of the heart
is going to be inflamed.
And so the first of the layers, or the innermost layer,
would be the endocardium, and so they can get an endocarditis.
Now, when they get an endocarditis,
they're going to get these tiny little vegetations on the endocardium,
particularly the endocardium of the mitral valve.
And so the endocarditis will actually involve valves preferentially,
and it's mostly going to involve the mitral valve.
Now, if there's an additional valve that will be involved,
it'll be the aortic.
So basically, it will involve the mitral valve,
and if there's a second valve, it'll be the mitral plus the aortic.
Now, when you get these little vegetations on the surface
or the very edge of the valve, that's going to lead to regurgitation,
and so one of the complications would be mitral valve regurgitation.
So that's the endocarditis.
Now, as far as the myocarditis is concerned,
the key problem will be that you'll get these bodies
within the myocardium called ashoff bodies.
And this is an image here of an ashoff body,
and you can see that we've got all these myocytes here.
I'm labeling them with M.
And then in the middle of these myocytes,
we've got this ashoff body.
Now, what's an ashoff body?
It is a focus of chronic inflammation with giant cells
and fibrinoid material,
which is really just all this degenerated collagen,
with a group of cells called the anichcal cells.
Now, the anichcal cells are particularly high yield,
and what they are are these histiocytes, these cells here,
with these slender wavy nuclei running down the middle.
And so they also call that the caterpillar nucleus.
Now, this is a hallmark cell, and examiners like to go after it.
And I'd like to just take you back and remind you that,
now, you've got this ashoff body,
and you're going to see some anichcal cells.
For example, I'm circling one.
And this is a very important finding in a patient
with acute rheumatic fever.
And that's because the myocarditis that occurs
in acute rheumatic fever is the most common cause of death
during the acute phase.
So if there's one thing that's going to kill the patient
with acute rheumatic fever,
it's going to be the myocarditis.
And what is the hallmark of the myocarditis
are going to be the ashoff bodies,
which contain anichcal cells.
So all of that is particularly high yield.
Now, recall that I told you that there would also be
pericarditis, and so the pericarditis can lead to a friction rub.
And so these patients can also develop a friction rub.
Now, the acute attack will eventually resolve,
assuming that the patient doesn't die from the myocarditis,
but it can progress to chronic disease.
So you can actually develop chronic rheumatic heart disease.
And that occurs when there's repeat exposure
to group A beta hemolytic strep,
which then results in a relapse of the acute phase.
And each time you relapse the acute phase,
it increases the risk for chronic rheumatic valvular disease.
And chronic rheumatic valvular disease is basically scarring
that occurs from a bunch of acute attacks.
This scarring will result in stenosis,
which means that you're going to tighten the valve
and make it difficult to push anything through it.
And it almost always involves a mitral valve.
Now, let's go back and remind ourselves
that acute rheumatic fever basically involves a mitral valve.
And then if it's going to involve another valve,
it'll involve the aortic beyond that.
And so, of course, the chronic disease will also
almost always involve the mitral valve.
It'll lead to thickening of the corda tendinae in the cusps,
and eventually that, of course, is going to produce stenosis.
Now, occasionally, it can also involve the aortic valve,
which would then lead to fusion of the commissures.
I'll show you a picture of that in a moment.
The other valves are less commonly involved.
Now, when you've got damage to these valves,
then the complication of a damaged valve will be endocarditis.
And you're going to hear more about that
in our discussions of endocarditis that are upcoming.
Here's an image of the aortic valve
that's involved by chronic rheumatic heart disease.
Again, the idea here is that you get scarring of the valve
with fusion of the commissures,
and that's particularly high yield.
So, let's go back and look at this.
This is the normal aortic valve,
and it should open like this,
so that you should have cusps one, two, and three.
And these cusps should sort of plug in
to the very edge of the aortic valve root.
Now, notice here that what's happening
is you've got this scarring here and here,
which is fusing these commissures,
these single edges of the valve,
which is fusing these commissures together.
And so, when you get fusion of the commissures,
what ends up happening is it reduces the orifice of the valve.
It actually then results in the formation of this space
that resembles a fish mouth,
and so this is also known as the fish mouth appearance of the valve.
Again, this is the aortic valve,
and the problem is that you're going to have stenosis
because you're not going to be able to completely open this valve.
Switching gears and moving to aortic stenosis,
this is a narrowing of the aortic valve orifice.
Now, again, this is the left ventricle here,
and of course, the aortic valve would be opening here.
If you narrowed the opening or the window of this valve,
that would be called aortic stenosis.
Now, normally, the valve opening is about four centimeters squared,
but in aortic stenosis, it becomes less than one centimeter squared.
Now, this is usually due to fibrosis and calcification,
so the idea is that it's a wear and tear disorder.
The more you bang on the valve, the more you use the valve over time,
the more it begins to fibrose and undergo dystrophic calcification,
and eventually, that then is going to result in stenosis of the valve.
This is going to present in late adulthood.
Again, the longer you live, the more you bang on the valve,
the more you degenerate the valve,
the more likely the disease is to occur.
And there's also an increased risk with bicuspid aortic valve.
Now, remember that the aortic valve is normally a tricuspid valve.
It has three cusps, and each of them is doing their job.
If you have a bicuspid valve, then the two cusps have to do the work of three,
and when the two cusps have to do the work of three,
there's going to be an increased risk for aortic stenosis,
and when it occurs, it'll occur earlier than the patients
who have the normal three cusps of the aortic valve.
Here's a picture of aortic stenosis.
Notice that you've got three cusps to the valve,
but also notice that this valve appears fibrotic and irregular.
Normally, it should be absolutely smooth,
i.e. each of the cusps should be absolutely smooth.
And so this is an example of aortic stenosis,
and you can see that it's decreasing the space through which blood can flow,
i.e. the window has become tight.
Now, we can also get aortic stenosis from chronic rheumatic valve disease.
So, as I stated just a few slides back,
one of the complications of chronic rheumatic valve disease is stenosis,
and you get stenosis of both the mitral valve as well as the aortic valve.
Now, how are we going to distinguish stenosis from rheumatic disease
versus stenosis from wear and tear?
Well, first of all, whenever you have rheumatic disease,
you're always going to have mitral stenosis as well,
because remember that rheumatic valvular disease always starts in the mitral valve,
and then may or may not involve the aortic valve.
And so if you've got stenosis of the aortic valve by itself,
it's not going to be rheumatic heart disease.
You've got to have stenosis of the mitral valve plus the aortic valve,
and that's the first point.
The second point is that the aortic valve will have fusion of the commissures
when there is chronic rheumatic heart disease.
Here again is a picture of the aortic valve from the patient with chronic rheumatic heart disease,
and remember that we had fusion of these commissures,
where the edges of the commissures got stuck together,
creating this fish mouth appearance.
For the purposes of comparing and contrasting, here is the aortic valve
in which you've had extensive wear and tear.
Now notice that there is no fusion of the commissures,
and again that's a major distinction from chronic rheumatic valve disease.
Regardless of the cause of aortic stenosis,
the patients will have a prolonged asymptomatic stage.
That's because there's going to be compensation,
such that the left ventricle will be able to push blood across that stenotic area.
When the left ventricle is pushing against the stenotic area,
it will eventually blow open that valve,
and when it blows it open, you'll hear a systolic ejection click,
and then as the valve opens,
all the blood will sort of move out in a big rush, giving you a crescendo,
and then eventually that will decrease, giving you a decrescendo murmur.
And so these are some of the hallmarks of aortic stenosis.
The complications of aortic stenosis include concentric left ventricular hypertrophy,
and so again, if this is the left ventricle here,
and the left ventricle has to pump against this tight stenotic aortic valve,
you're going to get hypertrophy of the muscle of the left ventricle.
In addition, patients can get angina and syncope with exercise.
The idea here is that because there is a stenosis,
there is a limited ability to increase blood flow across the valve,
and so therefore if there's exercise,
it's difficult to get extra blood to the brain and the heart,
and that can result in angina and syncope.
And finally, there can be a microangiopathic hemolytic anemia.
The idea here is that when the blood flows across the degenerated calcified valve,
some of the blood cells can rupture,
and that would give you a microangiopathic hemolytic anemia.
And so these are all important complications.
The treatment is based on the presence of the complications,
so you normally don't replace the valve until after the onset of the complications.
Moving on to aortic regurgitation, let's illustrate this.
Here is the left atrium and the left ventricle,
and recall that the left ventricle will push blood across the aortic valve during systole.
Now during diastole, this should seal, allowing for the blood to move forward.
However, if there is leakiness of this valve, that will result in regurgitation,
allowing some blood to move backward.
And that's the definition of aortic regurgitation.
This is the fact that the back flow of blood from the aorta into the left ventricle during diastole.
Now the most common cause of aortic regurgitation is a isolated aortic root dilatation.
So the idea here is that if this is the aortic root, and coming off the root are the valves,
then if there is a dilation of this aortic root, that is going to pull on the valves,
which will then increase the space between the valves, allowing for regurgitation backward into the left ventricle.
And so this is the most common cause, an isolated aortic root dilatation.
At the same time, you can get aortic root dilatation with a syphilitic aneurysm.
Remember the picture that I drew you during the vascular lectures.
If this is the aorta coming off the left ventricle, then if there is an aneurysm of the aorta in the thorax,
this aneurysm, or balloon-like dilatation, will pull on the aortic root.
And when it pulls on the aortic root, that's going to make this valve leaky,
so that blood will actually go backward during diastole.
And so this is another important cause.
But of course, it's not the most common cause, but it's another way by which you can dilate the aortic root.
And finally, if you damage the valve itself, if this is the aortic root, you've got these cusps of the valves coming off.
If you damage these valves, that will then result in aortic regurgitation.
And the example would be infectious endocarditis, which could potentially damage the valve, resulting in aortic regurgitation.
Now the clinical features will be that you'll have an early blowing diastolic murmur.
Now diastolic murmur, because the blood will go back during diastole.
And whenever you have blood going backwards, you often get a blowing murmur.
An additional clinical feature is that the patients will have something called a hyperdynamic circulation.
And this is particularly high yield to be aware of.
The idea here is that you've got the heart, and of course left atrium, left ventricle.
Let's just make up an arbitrary number and pretend that the heart pumps 100 milliliters each time it squeezes.
Now that 100 milliliters is going to go into the aorta, and then of course that's going to generate a blood pressure as it goes down through the rest of the system.
In aortic regurgitation, you're going to get some regurgitation of volume, so that this 100 milliliters now becomes 80, and so that would decrease the diastolic pressure.
And at the same time, with the return of 20 milliliters to the left ventricle, the next time it's going to pump out 120, and that's going to increase the stroke volume, and of course the stroke volume is going to then increase the systolic pressure.
So you're going to get an increase in the systolic pressure and a decrease in the diastolic pressure, and that is then going to widen something called the pulse pressure, which is the difference between the systolic and diastolic pressures.
Now, as there's this widening of the pulse pressure, the patients are going to have bounding pulses, they're going to have a pulsatile nail bed, they often can have head bobbing, especially on board examinations, and all of this is called a hyperdynamic circulation,
and it's based on the fact that the systolic pressure increases because of the increased stroke volume with the regurgitation, and the diastolic pressure decreases due to the fact that some blood is being regurgitated back into the heart.
Additional clinical features is that you'll get left ventricular dilatation, as you add additional volume back into the left ventricle, the left ventricle can dilate, and one of the important features of volume overload is that you get hypertrophy,
but it's an eccentric hypertrophy, where it involves one aspect of the ventricle as opposed to the entire concentric ventricle, and so they call that eccentric hypertrophy, and it's classically seen with volume overloaded states.
Now, the treatment will be valve replacement once left ventricular dysfunction develops.
Mitral valve prolapse is ballooning of the mitral valve into the left atrium during systole.
Let's just briefly illustrate this, so here you've got the left atrium, and this is the left ventricle, and then you've got the mitral valve here.
Now, this mitral valve is normally very tight, and so you can think of it sort of as a very firm kind of rubbery substance.
However, if there's degeneration of the valve, then that firm rubber would actually turn into this more myxoid or gel-like substance, making the valve more loose and floppy.
And that's what happens in mitral valve prolapse, is that you get myxoid degeneration of the valve, making it more floppy.
The etiology is usually not known.
However, it can be associated with, for example, Marfan syndrome or Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.
But in most cases, the etiology is not known.
Now, the idea here is that when this valve becomes floppy, then what's going to happen is that when the left ventricle is squeezing blood out down through the aortic valve,
this valve should normally become very tight, i.e., the mitral valve should normally become very tight and should close.
However, in this particular case, there's going to be a little bit of a ballooning backward of the mitral valve during systole,
and when that mitral valve balloons backwards, you're going to get a little bit of a click.
It's sort of like opening of a parachute.
And so when you open a parachute, you'd hear a loud noise, and in the same way, during systole, as this valve parachutes backwards,
you're going to hear a click in the middle of systole.
And that's one of the key clinical features, a mid-systolic click.
Now, in addition, there can be some regurgitation back across that valve.
There doesn't always have to be, but it often is present.
The complications of mitral valve prolapse are rare, but they include infectious endocarditis because the valve will be damaged over time,
arrhythmia, and severe mitral regurgitation.
Of course, as this valve is clicking backwards, it's going to get stretched, and as it gets stretched,
that's going to result in some leakiness to this valve, which would then result in mitral valve regurs.
The treatment is valve replacement.
The final point I'd like to make concerning mitral valve prolapse is this is a picture of mitral valve prolapse,
and you can see that this valve has become very loose and floppy, and it's sort of regurgitating back towards you,
because we're actually sitting in the atrium here looking at the valve as it comes back towards us.
Mitral regurgitation is when you get reflux of blood from the left ventricle into the left atrium during systole.
Again, the idea here is that you've got the left atrium here, you've got the left ventricle here.
This valve should normally become tight and shut when the left ventricle is squeezing and pushing blood forward during systole.
However, if this valve becomes loose, then during systole some of the blood can actually go backwards into the left atrium,
and that's called mitral valve regurg.
This usually arises as a complication of mitral valve prolapse, as I just stated in the prior slides.
Other causes would include left ventricular dilatation.
Again, if this is the standard picture that we keep drawing, and this is the left atrium and the left ventricle,
if you get dilation of the left ventricle, you're actually going to pull apart the leaflets of this valve, making this valve leaky.
Other causes listed here include infective endocarditis, which can damage the valve leaflets,
acute rheumatic heart disease.
Remember that in acute rheumatic heart disease, the most commonly involved valve is the mitral valve,
and the most common complication is where you get those little vegetations on the valve, resulting in mitral valve regurgitation.
And finally, papillary muscle rupture after a myocardial infarction can also give you mitral valve regurgitation.
Here again, you've got the left atrium, and this is the left ventricle.
Remember that the mitral valve has these little string-like tendine coming off the valve,
which are called the corda tendine, and they attach to the papillary muscles here.
And the papillary muscles help to keep this valve shut and closed during systole.
Now, if there's rupture of a papillary muscle, then you would not be able to keep this valve closed,
and you could get regurgitation back across that valve.
Clinically, the patients will have a holosystolic blowing murmur.
The idea here is that when the left ventricle is trying to squeeze blood forward during systole,
some of the blood would go backward.
Now, this could get louder with squatting or with expiration.
And the idea here is that if this is the left atrium and this is the left ventricle,
and the patient squats, when they squat, they're going to increase the resistance here.
So if less blood is going to be able to go forward because there's a higher pressure,
more blood will be squeezed this way.
And so the murmur would become louder when they're squatting.
In addition, the murmur will get louder with expiration.
The idea here is that when there's expiration, there's going to be an increase in the amount of blood
that enters into the left atrium.
That will then result in an increase in the blood in the left ventricle.
Now, during that cycle, when this increased blood is pushed this way,
there will also be increased blood regurgitating back this way,
which is going to make the murmur louder.
Mitral stenosis is when we have narrowing of the mitral valve orifice,
and the key circumstance in which we would see this would be chronic rheumatic valve disease.
Remember that chronic rheumatic valve disease preferentially involves the mitral valve,
and that it creates stenosis.
So chronic rheumatic disease creates stenosis, and acute rheumatic disease creates regurg.
And that's a high-yield sort of simple principle to bear in mind.
Now, what you're going to get here is an opening snap followed by a diastolic rumble.
Now, the idea here is very simple.
If this is the left atrium, and this is the left ventricle, and there's a stenosis here,
then the left atrium will push open the stenosis during diastole,
when it's feeding blood to the left ventricle,
and you'll get a little bit of a rumble after you blow open that window.
And so that's the key finding, as we've stated in the text,
an opening snap followed by a diastolic rumble.
One of the key complications of mitral stenosis is that you'll get volume overload of the left atrium.
Again, all of the blood in the left atrium will not be able to be pushed into the left ventricle
because of the stenosis.
And so eventually, you'll get volume overload with dilatation of the left atrium.
Now, the complications of this will be the following.
Number one, we'll get pulmonary congestion.
And that's because as you overload the left atrium,
you're also going to back up blood into the pulmonary circuit,
and so that'll result in pulmonary congestion.
And remember, the two complications of pulmonary congestion are going to be edema,
because we're going to increase the hydrostatic pressure in the vessels of the lung.
And number two, alveolar hemorrhage.
As the capillaries become engorged, they can rupture.
That will result in hemorrhage.
The macrophages within the airspace will consume the blood,
giving you hemocytorin-laden macrophages, also called heart failure cells.
And so those are the two complications of pulmonary congestion.
In addition, because there's excess blood volume within the pulmonary circuit,
we'll get pulmonary hypertension.
Of course, if there's pulmonary hypertension,
the right heart will have to pump against the pulmonary hypertension,
and eventually the right heart could fail.
And then finally, because there is going to be dilatation of the left atrium,
as you stretch that atrium, you're going to get abnormalities of the conducting system,
which is then going to result in atrial fibrillation.
And when you get atrial fibrillation, you're going to have abnormal movement of the wall,
which will result in stasis, which will then increase the risk of mural thrombi.
And so here is the classic image of a mural thrombus in the left atrium.
You can see this thrombus here up against the wall,
and it's due to the fact that you've got poor movement of the atrial wall,
resulting in stasis of the blood, increasing the risk of thrombosis.
And so this is called a mural thrombus.
And that concludes our discussion on valvular disorders.